So today's דף *daf* is דף פ"ח *Daf Peh-Chet* 88, and we
pick up at the very bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב' Paz Amud
Bet. *Peh-Zayin Amud Bet*, and we're in the middle of this whole
discussion about whether the air space over the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* counts
like the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach* for this הלכה halacha *Halacha* that when
you have a קרבן korban, *Korban* there, it's like it's already on
the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* and therefore the הלכה halacha *Halacha* is that
if it's פסול pasul *Pasul*, you don't take it down and so
it would apply even if it's over the air space. Before we
continue with that, I wanted to just say one mention about what
we did yesterday, because the גמרא'ס Gemara's *Gemara's* question about ריש לקיש
*Resh Lakish* asked רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, if you put, because the
משנה Mishnah *Mishna* says, if you put something in a כלי שרת
kli shares. *Kli Sharet*, that's also מקדש Mikdash *Mekadesh*, and ריש לקיש
*Resh Lakish* asked רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, does that mean that you
can also offer it up לכתחילה *Lechatchila* even if it's פסול pasul
*Pasul*? So what else would the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* mean? So, first
of all, so רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says what the alternative is, is
that the, one of the normal הלכות halachot *Halachos* of what a
כלי שרת kli shares *Kli Sharet* does is that it makes a
קרבן *Korban* at the level, literally it's מקדש *Mekadesh* that it gives
it this other level of sanctity, not just verbal sanctity, that now
it can't be redeemed. Now it's like fully designated or whatever and
it can't be redeemed, it's not just verbal sanctity and so on.
I mistakenly, and I just wanted to reiterate that this was a
mistake, I mistakenly had mentioned that it has an implication for מעילה
*Meila*, that is not correct. מעילה *Meila* applies as soon as the
verbal sanctity has taken place, actually it's a מפורש משנה mishna *Meforash
Mishna* in מעילה *Meila*. Going into a כלי שרת kli shares *Kli
Sharet*, let's say you have a מנחה minchah? *Mincha* and you sanctify
the flour and whatever, that is fully sanctified in terms of מעילה
*Meila*. כלי שרת klee sharet. *Kli Sharet* is, well, I mean, it
depends on the circumstance about whether it's going לה' *L'Hashem* or not,
anyway, whatever, but anyway, but let's say, well, but okay, if there
is verbal sanctity it's מעילה *Meila*. כלי שרת klee sharet *Kli Sharet*
has two primary נפקא מינות *Nafkamina's*. One is that it can't be
redeemed, and number two is, is that it's פסול pasul *Pasul* at
this stage if it's for with לינה lina, *Lina* and יוצא *Yotzei*
and פול יו *Ful Yo*. Like it's more susceptible to being invalid,
lower levels of טומאה tumah, *Tumah*, if it's taken out of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit Hamikdash* because if I sanctify my flour
and oil at home, it's not פסול posul *Pasul* because it's out
of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit Hamikdash*. Only after it goes
into a כלי שרת kli shares *Kli Sharet*, now it will become
פסול posul *Pasul* if it's taken out of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*. So anyway, that's just number one, that מעילה *Meila*
starts as soon as the verbal, כלי שרת kli shares *Kli Sharet*
gets it to this higher level where it's more susceptible to becoming
invalid and also that it can't be redeemed. Now the other thing
I did want to say is, there's a very long תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot*,
because תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is very bothered that he says all of
the evidence in so many different סוגיות *Sugyot* in ש"ס *Shas* is,
it doesn't matter if something's in a כלי שרת kli shares *Kli
Sharet*, if it's invalid you're not allowed to offer it לכתחילה *Lechatchila*
on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*. So what type of a הוה אמינא
*Hava Amina* did, you know, was there that לכתחילה *Lechatchila* you'd be
able to offer it on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*? He doesn't really
ever answer that question, he basically just says you'd have to give
these, these four אוקימתות ukimtot *Ukimtas* of all those גמרות *Gemarot*, but
obviously all the evidence is that once it's invalid even in a
כלי שרת kli shares *Kli Sharet* you can't offer it up. What
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* does suggest though without really, I mean, he raises
the question, he doesn't answer it, but what he does suggest as
an alternative to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* of what else could the משנה
mishna, *Mishna* mean? If it doesn't mean you're לכתחילה *Lechatchila* allowed to
offer it up, what else could it mean that a כלי שרת
*Kli Sharet* is מקדש *Mekadesh*? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, well what
it would mean would be, it's in the כלי שרת *Kli Sharet*
and it's on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *Mizbeach*. Okay, and then you don't
have to take it off. Now he says, well isn't that obvious,
it's on the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach*? He says no, because remember it's
not physically touching the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*, even if you assume that
the air space and this ties it into our discussion of the
מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach* is like the מזבח mizbe'ach, *Mizbeach*, but if it's
in a כלי שרת *Kli Sharet* maybe it's not considered in the
air space of the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*. That's classically a question that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks in all these different scenarios, if something
is in my vessel in your domain, is it in my domain
or your domain? Okay, so if something is in a כלי שרת
*Kli Sharet* on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach*, it could be that the
air space of the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* is like the מזבח mizbe'ach?
*Mizbeach*, if it was just out of the כלי שרת *Kli Sharet*
it would be on the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach* and you couldn't take
it down, but you wouldn't know for certain that if it's in
a כלי שרת *Kli Sharet* you're not, you're not, you know, that
you're, that you're allowed to leave it there. You might think פשיטא
*Pshita*. Okay, but that's the חידוש *Chiddush* of the משנה mishna *Mishna*.
So the first, the basic חידוש *Chiddush* of the משנה *Mishna* is
if it's in a כלי שרת *Kli Sharet* on the מזבח mizbe'ach.
*Mizbeach*, it is מקדש *Mekadesh* to the same degree as if it
were on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* directly. Okay, I know, I, okay
fine, you think it's פשיטא *Pshita*, it's not so פשיטא *Pshita*, it's
in its separate zone. Anyway, but ריש לקיש'ס *Resh Lakish's* question was,
if you didn't already put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach* are
you allowed to put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach *Mizbeach*? And again,
all the evidence in all other places in ש"ס *Shas* is that
you're not allowed to, okay, you can't לכתחילה *Lechatchila* put something on
the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* and make it a good קרבן *Korban* just
because it's in a כלי שרת *Kli Sharet*, but anyway, that was
the one sentence exchange between ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* and רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*. So I just wanted to sort of make it clear
that number one that תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* acknowledges that everything in ש"ס
*Shas* goes against that idea that לכתחילה *Lechatchila* you'd be allowed, and
B, he has a different הוה אמינא *Hava Amina* than רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* or different explanation of רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, not that the כלי
שרת *Kli Sharet* means for this הלכה halacha *Halacha* of פדיון *Pidyon*
or other type of things, but for this idea that if it's
in the כלי שרת *Kli Sharet* on the מזבח mizbe'ach? *Mizbeach* then
that obviously also counts as being on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbeach* as
well.
Well, let's say I haven't said to take your מנחה minchah? *Mincha*
as an example, anything all along and I bring it to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit Hamikdash*, I put it in the כלי
שרת *Kli Sharet*, I still haven't said anything, does כלי שרת *Kli
Sharet* then make it, you know?
No, I think that it has to be, good question, but I
think it has to be preceded with a verbal הקדשה *Haktasha*. But
anyway, alright, let's take a look now. So now we resume, now
we're at this question about whether the airspace counts as being on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach so that it doesn't have to come down if
it's in the airspace. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara and, you know,
the גמרא Gemara's had a point, well if it's on the ramp,
obviously you had to lift it up to bring it there, that
shows that the airspace counts as the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Why don't we
say lifting it up is like you took it off? And then
the גמרא's Gemara basic answer is oh you dragged it, okay. So
it has these אוקימתות about ways in which it could stay on
touching the מזבח mizbe'ach. without just being in the airspace, but maybe
the airspace is considered off the מזבח. mizbe'ach, So now the גמרא
Gemara continues at the bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב'. So the גמרא
Gemara says as follows.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. להכי אתא, Lehachi ata, two lines from the bottom, מי איפשיט.
Mi ifshit. Let's at least use this whole discussion about the bird
sacrifices which got into a whole discussion before about a פגול piggul
thought, let's use it to actually prove the opposite, I betcha, דאויר
מזבח כמזבח דמי, De'avir mizbe'ach kemizbe'ach dami, the airspace counts like the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Why? דאי סלקא דעתך אויר מזבח לאו כמזבח דמי, De'ei
salka dach'tach avir mizbe'ach lav kemizbe'ach dami, so חטאת העוף
פסולה היכי מזה מדמה? chatat ha'of pesula heichi maza midamah? So you
have an invalid חטאת העוף. chatat ha'of. You did a מליקה melika
on a חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, you did it שלא לשמה, shelo
lishma, it's invalid. But remember, one of the הלכות we said before
was, assuming birds are included in this category of מזבח מקדש, mizbe'ach
mekadesh, that even if it's an invalid bird, you're allowed to leave
it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so I did this invalid חטאת
העוף. chatat ha'of. Now, I'm allowed to leave it on the מזבח,
mizbeach. which presumably means it's here in the מזבח airspace or whatever
it is, and I'm allowed to sprinkle the blood, even though it's
invalid, because it's already on the מזבח. Now תוספות Tosfos says how
do you know that this הלכה halacha of you're allowed to keep
it on the מזבח means the blood? Maybe it meant the after
you put the meat up or whatever it is, but of course
there's no meat of a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of anyway. So, but
we assume it means the blood. So since you're there with the
חטאת העוף chatat ha'of on the מזבח, you're allowed to finish the
job and put the blood up because the blood is already there.
But one minute, the blood isn't there. The blood isn't on the
מזבח. The blood is only in the airspace of the מזבח. You're
only holding the bird in the airspace of the מזבח. So how
are you allowed to put the blood on the מזבח? הוי ליה
ירוד. Havlei yerud. It's like it's something that has been taken off
of the altar because it's only in the airspace, right? So you
did the מליקה. melika. Okay, you're holding the bird here. Here's the
wall of the מזבח or whatever, but it's right now not on
the מזבח. It might be in the airspace, but it's not on
the מזבח. So how are you allowed to do this? You have
to just remove it. It's off the מזבח right now. שאר פסולים
היכי זרקו מדמיה? She'ar pesulim heichi zarku midamei? How about something else?
Remember the משנה included a case of let's say you שחט shachted
it also שלא לשמה shelo lishma or with a פגול piggul thought
or whatever you did, right? So in that type of a case,
so we say according to the opinion that included in the things
you don't take off the altar are the blood. Remember we had
a debate, does it include liquids, blood and wine? Let's say it
includes blood. So I caught the blood בפיסול befisul or whatever the
case was, בטומאה, betumah, whatever the case was, it was טמא. tamei.
Anyway, and I brought the blood and I placed it down on
the altar. And now according to the opinion that the idea of
מזבח includes liquids, the הלכה is, okay, the liquid, now that the
blood is sitting on the altar, I can still go ahead and
leave it there and I can presumably throw it. But I'm not
just going to leave it there, I'm going to put it and
throw it on the side of the מזבח. Well how do I
throw it on the side of the מזבח? It's sitting there. As
soon as I lift it up and try to get it at
a distance and throw it, I'm, you know, I am no longer
touching the מזבח. I might be able to do it to be
in the airspace, but I'm no longer touching. So as soon as
I try to use the blood that I left on the altar,
I'm taking it off and it can't be used. Okay, so how
do you if the הלכה though is that the blood is one
of the things you're allowed to leave there and meaning ultimately use
it once it's there, that shows that the airspace still counts as
the מזבח itself. So the גמרא Gemara says דמגלה
להו. Demagleh lehu. So the גמרא Gemara's says no, you don't have
to remove it, you don't have to get it off the מזבח.
Let's say you שחט shachted the bird, okay, and again, you know,
I don't know at which stage as you שחט shachted it are
you touching it, but basically you got, you're holding the bird right
up against the wall and you שחט shachted it like that. So
it's constantly touching the wall of the מזבח. Okay, and if I
got my blood over here at the top of the מזבח, rather
than lifting it up and throwing it, what I just do is
I just, I don't know, somehow I pour it straight on and
it touches and it never leaves contact with the מזבח.
So you don't actually have to throw it?
So that's what the גמרא's Gemara's going to say. So the גמרא's
Gemara. going to say הא הזיה היא? Ha haza'ah hi? You call
that sprinkling? מיצוי היא. Mitzuy hi.
It's considered squeezing out, right? By an עולה olah you squeeze out,
by a חטאת chatat you stand at a distance by the bird.
And by the normal קרבן, הזריקה, ha-zerikah, you call that throwing? שפיכה
היא. Shefichah hi. It's spilling. That doesn't count as an act of
the right act with the blood. ועוד דרך הזאה בכך דרך זריקה
בכך, Ve'od derech haza'ah bekach derech zerikah bekach, which is a different
variation, but rather than saying we're categorizing it as something else, even
if we're not categorizing it as something else, we're just categorizing it
as a very weird הזיה, haza'ah, a very weird זריקה. zerikah. But
a weird is also a problem. If it's not the normal way
of doing it, even if you don't call it something else, that
should make it not valid. So be it, therefore look, all the
evidence is that yes, once the stuff is on the מזבח. Obviously
the airspace counts as the מזבח *mizbe'ach* itself. So once that's true,
what was your question about the airspace? אמר רב אשי אי דנקטי
ליה בראש מזבח הכי נמי *Amar Rav Ashi ee dinakloo berosh mizbe'ach
hachi nami*.
You're right. Our question about airspace does not apply to the fact
that if your feet are on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and you're lifting
and the bird or the blood or whatever it is is in
the airspace, that's considered anchored in the מזבח *mizbe'ach* because your feet
are on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. So even if it's in the airspace,
if you're holding it and you're on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, that's on
the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. So what was our question about the airspace? כי
קאמר דתלינו בקניא מאי תיקו *Kee kammar detaleenoo bekanya mai, teyko*. Our
case was that you're not standing on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. You've got
it at like on a
fishing pole, like you got it on a hook. אין דרך עבודה
בכך *In derech avoda bekach*? Okay, what? No, no, no. It's not
the עבודה *avoda*. The point is I've got this meat of
that's I don't know I got these entrails that were טמא *tamei*.
Okay, if I were to get them onto the ramp, they'd be
allowed to stay on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and then I'd be allowed
to pick them up and walk them because my feet are on
the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. But they never made it yet to the ramp.
What happened was was let's say, I don't know, let's say I
had them in a big, you know, in a in a something
with a long stick, right? And it's got and whatever, or whatever,
I just have it in a basket and I'm standing off the
ramp and I'm holding these entrails over the airspace of the ramp
without me standing on the ramp. So the question is is it
now like the entrails have touched the ramp of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*
that now I'm allowed to offer them up? Okay, so you don't
have to make an absurd case, like my example of the fishing
pole was a little absurd. We're going to throw them and hover
them right over the top of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. No, it could
just be I'm standing off the ramp but they are being suspended
over the airspace of the ramp or over the airspace of the
מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Is it like they have touched the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, or
you know, is it like that they're on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and
now they're allowed to be brought up and burnt? So that's a
good question we don't have any evidence because none of our cases
were that case. So that's a question that we leave unanswered. But
yes, if you're standing on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, wherever you're holding the
thing, they're also considered to be on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on, next משנה *Mishna*. Now since we
talked about כלי שרת *klei shares* sanctifying and as we said before,
the primary aspect of sanctifying is that you can't redeem stuff in
it and that it's more susceptible to becoming invalid and those types
of things, now we're going to get to the parameters of when
do כלי שרת *klei shares*, when do they sanctify the things that
are in them? So let's take a look. כלי לח kli lach
מקדשין mikadshin. את הלח halach, *Klei lach mekadesh et halach*. So the
vessels used for liquids, you know, all the types of bowls and
dishes and whatever, all those things sanctify liquids that are put in
them: wine and blood, etc. ומדות יבש yavesh מקדשות את היבש *Umidos
yavesh mekadesh et hayavesh*. And dry measures
sanctify dry things that are put in them.
Will you have
a hybrid, like a מנחה mincha, *Mincha*, you have oil and flour?
We're going to get to that. So things that are used for
measuring out flour primarily is what you would measure out, those sanctify
dry things but not liquids. Now before we continue, רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
asks a question. Why does it call it כלי הלח k'lei halach
*klei halach* and מדות היבש *midot hayavesh*? Why does it call it
vessels used for liquids and measures used for dry? Why don't you
use the word measures for both or vessels for both? So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*'s answer is well, because for the liquids you had all
you had things that were used for measuring, you had measuring cups
and you had thing, you know, you'd have to measure out the
right amount of wine and the right amount of oil, and you
also had things that were not used for measuring, just a bowl
that you would catch the blood in, a bowl you would put
the מנחה mincha *Mincha* in. Whereas for the dry stuff, you would
only use it for measuring. You would never use something for just
סתם stam *stam* holding something for dry if it wasn't used for
measuring. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* doesn't like this answer.
So no, but he's saying if it's only used for measuring then
you'd think it should certainly say מדה *mido* by the dry.
That's why it does say מדות *midos* by the dry.
מדות היבש *Midot hayavesh*.
So that's what רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says, it only says dry measures
because there was no dry vessels that were not used for measuring.
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* doesn't like this, and I want to read the
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* first. It's fun because he brings us a list
of counterexamples to רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, but then I want to hear
get your thoughts about what you think תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*'s answer to
this question is. So מדות היבש *midot hayavesh*, if you look at
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, he says: פירש בקונטרס דהכי קרי ליה ליבש מדה
וללח כלי שאין שום כלי במקדש ליבש אלא שתי מדות *Peirush bakuntres
dehachi kari lei layavesh mida velalach kli she'ein shum kli mikdash layavesh
o kli bamikdash layavesh ela shtei midot*. There was only two things
that were used for dry and they were measures, עשרון issaron וחצי
עשרון issaron *issaron vechatzi issaron*. That's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. The
only dry things you had were measures. ותימא הוי איכא ביזא בפרק
הקומץ רבה והוי איכא מחתה לקטורת *Veteima, hava ika biza beperek hakometz
raba, vahava ika machta lektoret*, right, the thing that they would use
for the incense that they would just scoop it out and that
wouldn't be for measure. Okay, והוי איכא כף והוי איכא מחתשת בשבועות
והוי איכא בזיכין ושלחן *vahava ika kaf, vahava ika machteshet bishvuot, vahava
ika bazichin veshulchan*. Okay, so you got to love it, תוספות *Tosafot*
says: but there's this and this and this, so he's got a
lot of counterexamples, so you'd have to go through all of them
and figure out why רש"י *Rashi* wasn't didn't think that those were
relevant. Anyway, so תוספות *Tosafot* says: ופירוש רבינו תם דהכי קרי ליה
ליבש מדה ולא כלי לפי שביבש יכולים למדוד מחוק או גדוש בכל
ענין שירצה *upeirush Rabbeinu Tam dehachi kari lei layavesh mida velo kli
lefi shebeyavesh yecholim limdod machuk o gadush bechol inyan sheyirtzeh*. Because
with something dry you can measure something whether it's like leveled, you
can level off the top or you can pile stuff up. Okay,
I mean if you're piling it, if you're having it, you know,
as a mound, I don't know how much you're measuring it. אבל
דבר לח lach לא שייך מידה גבי. But by liquid things, liquid
things you can't measure so well. Why not? שמידת לח אינה שווה.
Shemidat lach einah shaveh. The liquid measure isn't the same. דדבר לח
אינו יכול להיות גדוש. D'davar lach eino yachol lihyot gadush. First of
all, it can't be in a, like it can't, you know, have
a mound at the top. Okay, so that means you measure bad?
Yeah, I don't understand this תוספות which is why we're reading it
together, maybe one of you can explain it to me. ופעמים שמידת
לח זה יתיר מזה. U'pe'amim shemidat lach zeh yateir mizeh.
Sometimes liquid using the liquid for different things are different. Why? כמו
מידת יין יתיר ממידת מים לפי שיין עביו טפי. K'mo midat yayin
yateir mimidat mayim lefi sheyayin avyo tfei. Now
I don't understand that. It's true that wine is thicker, but that
just means that it's more weight. If these are volume measures, okay,
they're not weight measures. And you know what? If a dry measure
is a volume measure, it'll also be different based on what you're
weighing in it, what the what the weight will be, right? So
what does he mean it's thicker? Does he mean because it's thicker
there'll be a more of a what's it called meniscus? Is that
the thing that's called when you try to anyway, you know, more
surface tension or whatever. Anyway, וכן שמן מיין ולהכי לא קרו ליה
מידה. V'chen shemen miyayin u'lehachi lo karu leh midah.
I have no idea what תוספות is talking about. So because somehow
it's liquid, you know there's only surface tension and you can't get
it to pile and because there's different thicknesses of the things you're
measuring, you can't really call it a measure the same way you
call something dry a measure. I really don't know what he's talking
about about the fact that you can't actually have it mound and
you can only have it flat. I mean,
if what he means is that by the dry measure you would
mostly measure the same stuff, which would be flour, so in a
certain way it was a better measure because it wasn't only a
measure of volume, it was roughly also a good measure of weight,
whereas by liquids, it was a volume, it served as a volume
measure but it didn't really serve as a weight measure. So we're
not going to call it a measure to the same degree because,
I mean fine, but I still don't really get his point about
the, I mean about the what do you call it about whether
it has a mound or not have a mound or whatever. Okay,
back to the משנה. Anyway, so the liquid vessels sanctify liquids and
the dry vessels sanctify dry. אין כלי הלח מקדשת את היבש ולא
היבש מקדשת את הלח. Ein k'lei halach mekadeshet et hayavesh v'lo hayavesh
mekadeshet et halach. And they don't sanctify if you happen to put
wine into a dry measure or flour into a liquid vessel, it
would not sanctify it. Now we're going to have to see if
that literally means it because רש"י says basically that especially since רש"י
says that they would only have dry measures, you know, they wouldn't
have vessels that weren't used for measuring for dry. So what did
you do when you had your מנחה? mincha, After you had your
flour and you added a little bit of oil, where would you
put it? So רש"י says well, you wouldn't put it in a
dry measure, you would
put it in one of the standard vessels used for liquids, you
know, just a normal type of a vessel. Well, I mean if
you, you know, so says well, if you so רש"י says so
then that sanctifies it, right? But that's like a liquid measure, right?
For רש"י pretty much like everything is called a liquid measure. Every
generic thing is called a liquid measure except right you got two
things here, these are your dry measures, right? That's your עשרון issaron,
and your חצי עשרון. chatzi issaron. These are your two dry measures,
you know, half, right? And everything else, this is called יבש yavesh.
or מידות יבש. midot yavesh. And everything else is called כלי הלח
k'lei halach. because everything else is just like, you know, whether it's
used as a measure, you know, whatever it is, right? You know,
it's all these different types of things and they're not necessarily used
for measuring. I mean, they'd have measures too. So you go ahead,
you take your flour, you mix with oil. Now where are you
going to put it as a מנחה? mincha, You're not going to
keep it in a measuring thing, you've mixed with oil anyway so
it's too big. You're going to put it in one of these
כלי הלח. k'lei halach So what does it mean that the כלי
הלח kli halach, don't sanctify a solid? Okay, this is still fundamentally
a solid, it's not a liquid where your flour mixed with oil,
so we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay,
now
כלי הקודש שניקבו. K'lei hakodesh shenikbu. Now let's say you had a
hole in one of these vessels. אם עושים בהן מעין מלאכתן. Im
osim bahen me'ein melachtan. Well, the question is, is it still considered
a vessel? Okay, so we have questions like this by טומאה, tumah,
okay, but here's the question by כלי המקדש, k'lei hamikdash, when is
a vessel still considered a
vessel? אם עושים בהן מלאכתן שהיו עושים. Im osim bahen melachtan shehayu
osim. If it can still do similar to the functions it was
doing when they were unbroken when it didn't have a hole. ואינן
שלמים. v'einan shleimin. רש"י says the real reading is כשהן שלמים. keshehen
shleimin. If it can still function as they used to function when
they were not did not yet have a hole in it, okay,
מקדשין. Then they still work. So if it's got a little hole
but there was something that was basically used, if the flour's pouring
out of the hole or if it used to be that you
used it for flour but now you can use it for I
don't know when the flour's mixed with oil so it won't spill
out. But you used to be able to use it
for simple flour. But now all you know used to use it
for blood, now that it's got a hole you can't use it
for blood but you can use it for מנחות. minchot. That's That's
no good. But if the hole is such that you can still
use it in the way you used to be used before, then
it's still considered a vessel, and then it still sanctifies.
Wait, so what's the change in כשהן?
k'shehen? כשהן. k'shehen. Right. אם עושין בהן מלאכתן שהיו עושים כשהן שלמים.
Im osin bein melachtan shehayu osin k'shehen shleimim. Okay, that's what I
read together. All right, you read it all together. If you can
still- if it's not just it can still be used, it can
still be used in the same way it used to be used.
If the hole's on the top, let's say, like on the instead
of on the bottom for like, for blood.
Right, or you used to use it for something- if you used
it for blood and now you can only use it for a
מנחה, mincha because blood will run out, but a מנחה mincha won't,
you know, then that's not okay. But if you could use it
before for- before it was generally used for מנחה, mincha, now it's
used for מנחה, mincha that's fine. Or as you say, if the
hole's on the top, so it doesn't really affect its use. Right.
ואם
לאו אין מקדשין. V'im lav ein mekaddshin. And if not, they stop
being a כלי שרת. וכולן אין מקדשין אלא בקודש. V'chullan ein mekaddshin
ella bakodesh. They only have this effect if they're used in the
עזרה, Azarah, since one of the effects of כלי שרת is that
it's now- it's now- the thing that's put in a כלי שרת
will become פסול pasul if you take it out of the עזרה.
Azarah. It sanctifies it that now it's נפסל ביוצא. nifsal b'yotzei. So
therefore it only has this effect when it's in the entire קודש
kodesh complex and setting and context and it's in the עזרה. Azarah.
Okay.
I thought קודש kodesh was the היכל? Heichal?
No, it's used differently. Yeah. In this context, it means the עזרה.
Azarah. Okay, yeah.
So wait, if I'm in the עזרה Azarah and I accidentally take
it out, and then you know...
Then you put something in it, right. After you put something in
it, you took it out, then- then the thing already was sanctified
and now it's פסול ביוצא. pasul b'yotzei.
No, I took it out to begin with, right? I took it
out, and then I put it in.
But it automatically then becomes- when I put it back in?
In קודש? kodesh?
Yeah. That's a good point, I would assume so. That's- I assume
it's the act of putting something in it, the thing being in
it. אמר שמואל: לא שנו אלא מדות, אבל מזרקות מקדשין. Amar Shmuel:
Lo shanu ella middos, aval mizrakos mekaddshin.
This idea that the כלי לח lach? is what I was saying
before according to רש"י, that the liquid vessels don't work for dry,
that's only liquid measures don't use for dry. When the משנה said
liquid doesn't use for dry, to use a liquid measure for to
put something dry in it, that's completely not relevant and therefore it
doesn't sanctify. Liquid measures are for liquid, dry measures are for dry.
Okay? But if you have a simple bowl, okay, and that bowl
is generic, so we would normally categorize it under liquid vessels. But
it's not a liquid measure, it's a bowl. So bowls can be
used for solids, okay? Those are
generic, שנאמר: שניהם מלאים סולת. Shene'emar: Shneihem m'le'im soles. Both of these
מזרקות, mizrakos, both of these like bowls, it says filled with flour.
So you see here's a bowl, which normally we identify with something
for liquid, okay, and nevertheless filled with flour means it's- it's appropriate
for to be filled with flour. Okay, so really you've got three
categories. You've got מדות לח, middos lach, מדות יבש, middos yavesh,
and מדות לח, middos lach, okay? And your מדות לח middos lach
are like for, you know, very clear things, that let's say you
know, lines or whatever, and you know, whatever, very precise, okay? And
this, you know, you can't use one, you can't use- you can
only use this for לח and you can only use this for
יבש. And then we're going to call something כלי הלח, but it's
really not הלח, it's really just סתם כלים, stam keilim, it's really
bowls. So even though conceptually we tend to think about them as,
you know, as whatever, you know, as liquids, okay, the point is
that these are things which work both for, you know, both for
liquids and for solids. So when it says this only works for
dry and this only works for- this only works for liquids, this
only works for dry, it's talking about the measures. Things that are
סתם כלים stam keilim work for everything. Okay? שנאמר: שניהם מלאים סולת.
Shene'emar: Shneihem m'le'im soles. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא: מנחה לח
ליה היא? Amar lei Rav Acha midifti l'Ravina: Mincha lach lei hi?
What do you mean? How do you prove it from this case
about those, you know, about those bowls or whatever they were filled
with flour? It's not just- it's not just flour, it's not just
dry flour. It's flour and oil.
But does it make it לח?
So that's the גמרא'ס answer. So you can't prove from that that
סתם it works for dry. אמר ליה: לא נצרכה אלא ליבש שבה.
Amar lei: Lo nitzecha ella l'yavesh shebah. So the first answer is,
even if it's mixed with oil, there are parts of it, the
flour, that are not mixed with oil. And those too presumably are
sanctified. It's not just sanctifying the stuff that's been thoroughly mixed. איבעית
אימא Ibayis eima if you want I could tell you, מנחה לגבי
דם כיבש דמי, mincha lgabei dam k'yavesh dami, like Michael's saying. Look,
still a מזרק, mizrak, you know, from the word לזרוק lizrok is
presumably something that classically is used for catching and throwing the blood.
And nevertheless something that fundamentally is used for real liquid, to put
in it some mixture of flour and oil, relative to a real
liquid, that's dry. And nevertheless it still works for it. Now you
could still say, fine, it works for a relative case, not a
case that's absolutely dry, but he feels that's- that's pretty much enough
evidence that even if something is made for real liquid, it doesn't
have to be limited to a liquid as long as it's not
a measuring vessel. Okay. אמר שמואל: כלי שרת אין מקדשין אלא שלמים.
Amar Shmuel: Klei shares ein mekaddshin ella shleimim. First of all they
have to be whole. That's the point of our משנה, that if
somehow they're broken, again not any little crack, a crack that makes
them not usable the way they used to be, okay. So number
one they have to be whole, okay, and- and I
mean whole, they can't have holes in them. Okay, אין מקדשין אלא
מלאים, ein mekaddshin ella m'le'im, they have to be filled. This is
what... What we're going to get to, if you basically were supposed
to put a certain measure into it. It doesn't mean it has
to literally be filled to the top, it has to have the
full measure you were going to put into it.
So if I put a half עשרון issaron into the עשרון, issaron,
it won't work?
Well, we'll see the specifics in a minute, but yes. But right
now we're not even talking about the measures, we're talking about here.
I have an עשרון issaron, of a מנחה mincha that I want
to put into this vessel, okay, we're not to measure it, just
to put it in, okay, but I only put half the amount
in that I was eventually going to put in. I haven't put
in the full עשרון, I've only put half the מנחה mincha. in.
It doesn't work. ואין מקדשין אלא מתוכן, Ve'ein mekadshin ela mitokan, and
only stuff that's on the inside of them. So what we're going
to see this is going to exclude is if they, if they're
overfull and they're mounding on the top over, over the, you know,
the lip, that it doesn't sanctify. It has to fully be within
the walls of the vessel. You mean over like the whole area?
I go ahead and I fill this and it's like this, then
the only stuff that gets sanctified is the stuff that's actually in
the air space of the vessel, in the actual, you know, volume
of the vessel, not the stuff that's mounded on top, okay, only
stuff that's actually inside of it.
ואמרי לה, Ve'amrei lei, some say אין מקדשין אלא שלמים, ein mekadshin
ela sheleimim, that the vessels have to be complete, have to be,
you know, unbroken, ומלאים, umele'im, and full, they can't have just put
the half amount into it, ומי בפנים, umi bipnim, and on the
inside. Now, Rashi says ומי בפנים umi bipnim means
inside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash in the עזרה, azara, but then
it's like a completely different point. תוספות says no, מביפנים mibipnim is
just a different word for מתוכן. mitokan. It has to be inside
of it, not outside of it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what's the difference between the word מתוכן mitokan
and
מביפנים? mibipnim? איכא בינייהו בירורי מדות. Ika beinaihu beirurei middot. So בירורי
מדות beirurei middot is exactly this, the mounding that goes higher than
the measure, the mounding that goes on top of it. So if
you said מתוכן, mitokan, מתוכן mitokan means the mound doesn't count, okay,
it has to literally be inside of it. If you mean מביפנים,
mibipnim, it means like if you put something, I don't know, if
you flipped it over and put something, imagine some type of a
thing, you know, had a little, sometimes these things just have a
little thing like that, you know what I mean? So let's say,
יוסי, Yossi, you flipped it over and you kept something in the
hollow on the back, that would be מבחוץ, mibachutz, but מביפנים mibipnim
doesn't mean it has to end at the lip. All of this
counts as מביפנים. mibipnim. So מביפנים mibipnim and מתוכן mitokan are basically
saying the same thing, inside not outside, but the nuance difference is
מתוכן mitokan means it only goes up to the actually, up to
the lip. Higher than the lip, it doesn't sanctify. And מביפנים mibipnim
means no, anything that's, you know, as long as it's not on
the outer part of it, even if it's a mound, if, you
know, that's considered מביפנים mibipnim and it does sanctify. So that's the
question, whether it sanctifies the mounding on the top. ומתנייתא תנא, Umatniyata
tana, in a ברייתא braita we taught, אין מקדשין אלא שלמים ומלאים
ומתוכן ובפנים. ein mekadshin ela sheleimim umele'im umitokan ubipnim. Now the difference
from בפנים bipnim to מביפנים mibipnim is like what רש״י Rashi said.
בפנים bipnim is clearly means inside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. inside
the עזרה. azara. אמר רב אשי אמר רב יוחנן, Amar Rav Ashi
amar Rav Yochanan, לא שנו אלא שאין דעתו להוסיף. lo shanu ela
she'ein da'ato lehosif. This idea that if you put in only a
partial measure it doesn't sanctify, that's only when you, you were done.
You put in a half of an עשרון, so it doesn't get
sanctified because that's not the full amount you need for your מנחה,
mincha okay, but if you're basically are like putting it in in
the process of filling it up, in the process of filling it
up, okay, it sanctifies as it's being filled, okay?
I have to tell you that's not so obvious to me. You
could say the opposite, you could say if you're in the process
it doesn't sanctify something in the middle of a process. But here
his proposition is, is that it only sanctifies it if conceptually it's
part of a full measure. So if you're done at your half
measure, it's not sanctified. If you're it's a process and it's going
to become a full measure, it does sanctify. Okay, אבל דעתו להוסיף
ראשון ראשון קודש. aval da'ato lehosif rishon rishon kodesh. Okay, if you're
adding it then every bit that as you're filling it it does
become sanctified. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it's taught similarly מלאים,
mele'im, because this, we get this from the word שניהם מלאים. sheneihem
mele'im. So מלאים mele'im means, you know, this idea that it has
to be presumably שלם, shalem, but it also has to be filled.
אין מלאים אלא שלמים. Ein mele'im ela sheleimim. אמר רבי יוסי אימתי
בזמן שאין דעתו להוסיף, Amar Rabbi Yossi eimatai bizman she'ein da'ato lehosif,
if you're done before you've filled it up, אבל דעתו להוסיף, aval
da'ato lehosif, if you actually are in the process of getting to
the full measure, ראשון ראשון קודש, rishon rishon kodesh, it's sanctified. All
right, moving on. אין כלי הלח מקדש. Ein klee halach mekadesh.
So this idea that a liquid vessel doesn't sanctify a dry or
a liquid measure doesn't sanctify a dry and a dry measure doesn't
sanctify a liquid. So the גמרא Gemara now says, אמר רב ואיתימא
רב אסי, Amar Rav ve'iteima Rav Assi, אין מקדשין ליקרב אבל מקדשין
ליפסל. ein mekadshin likarev aval mekadshin lipasel. This idea that if you're,
if you're doing it the wrong type of a, of a thing,
it doesn't sanctify it, it means it doesn't sanctify it so that
now it's not, it doesn't enable it to be offered up. But
it does sanctify it so that it does have the negative consequences,
as it were, about being sanctified in a כלי שרת. Remember, what
did I tell you that a כלי שרת sanctifies means? You can't
redeem it, it'll become פסול pasul? if a טבול יום tvul yom
touches it, it'll become פסול if you take it out of the
בית המקדש. Okay,
so those types of things, right, are and it'll become פסול if
it stays overnight. So all these ways of becoming invalid, of making
it more susceptible, it has all those negative consequences, but because it's
not the right vessel, it doesn't raise it to the level that
now your מנחה can let's say be offered up on the מזבח.
Okay, so אבל מקדשין לפסול. aval mekadeshin l'pasul. איכא דמתני להא. Ika
demasni l'ha. Some teach that not in our case that you use
the wrong vessel, but on the following teaching. אין מביאין מן החותם
ומנחת בהמה וביכורים מן המדומע. Ein mevi'in min hachosem umenachas behema uvikurim
min hameduma. You can't bring all of these types of, you know,
מנחות menachos and wine offerings etc. from מדומע. meduma. What does מדומע
meduma mean? Normally מדומע meduma means a mixture of תרומה terumah and
חולין. chullin. So why couldn't you bring it from a mixture of
תרומה terumah and חולין? chullin? So there's a principle that says ממשקה
ישראל, mimashkeh Yisrael, that you're only allowed to offer on the altar
what is permissible to be eaten by the Jewish people. So רש״י
Rashi says that means it has to be permissible to be eaten
by all of the Jewish people. If you actually cannot offer תרומה
terumah on the altar because that's only edible by כהנים, Kohanim, which
is a very interesting idea. So even something holier, because it's not
accessible to all the Jewish people, it can't be offered on the
altar. תוספות disagrees with this. תוספות says מדומע meduma means a mixture
of something like ערלה, orlah, okay, if it's made from ערלה, orlah,
right, the first three years of forbidden fruit, or whatever, that and
it's mixed with non-ערלה, orlah, that's what you can't offer. And certainly
as the משנה as the ברייתא braisa continues, it says ואין צריך
לומר מערלה וכלאי הכרם, v'ein tzorich lomar me'orlah v'kilay hakerem, certainly if
it's direct ערלה orlah and כלאיים kilayim you can't offer. Okay, so
number one, it's an interesting question. Is it just saying you can't
offer it if it's literally forbidden fruit, or you can't offer it
if even if it's just תרומה? terumah? רש״י Rashi interestingly says even
תרומה terumah can't be offered on the altar. But anyway, here you
have your מנחה made from, let's say, a simple case of ערלה
orlah or כלאיים, kilayim, right, these stuff that's really forbidden to be
eaten cannot be offered up as a מנחה. Now, ואם הביא לא
קידש. ve'im heivi lo kidesh.
And if you did go ahead and tried to make your מנחה
from this forbidden flour and you put it in a vessel, you
didn't, it did not, you didn't sanctify it. Okay, אמר רב ואיתימא
רב אסי, Amar Rav v'isima Rav Assi, לא קידש לקרב, lo kidesh
le'karev,
it means putting it in the vessel doesn't make it now acceptable
to be offered up. Okay, that gets to our earlier question that
we started today with ריש לקיש ורבי יוחנן, Reish Lakish v'Rabbi Yochanan,
putting something פסול in a כלי שרת doesn't allow it to be
offered up. אבל קידש לפסול, aval kidesh le'pasul, but it is sanctified
that now it's more susceptible to being invalid. Now, of course, what
does that mean? Until now I've been saying what does invalid mean?
It becomes, you know, certain types of טומאה, you know, לינה, etc.
Of course, this stuff is invalid already. What difference does it make
if it's invalid again? So here really the relevance is like רש״י
Rashi said earlier, it means that it can't be redeemed, okay? So
again, putting something in a כלי שרת has the positive value most
of the time of allowing it now to be offered, but it
also has the consequence because it's holier that it can't be redeemed
and that it's more easily susceptible to becoming invalid. So here we're
saying this type of stuff, which is these non-kosher grain products, okay,
yes, a כלי שרת does not make it now acceptable to be
offered, but a כלי שרת does make it more have the negative
consequences, make it more susceptible for invalidity and so on, okay? The
same way using
a measure of solid for liquids or liquids for solids, they don't
raise it to the right level to be offered, but they do
raise it enough that make it have all more of the negative
consequences. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
now we're going to get to this issue about what happens if
they have a crack in it or something.
כלי קודש שניקבו אין מתיכין אותן. Klei kodesh shenikvu ein matichin osan.
If they get a hole in them, you cannot go ahead and
like melt them in order to fill their hole, you can't put
them over some fire in order to, you know, fill up the
hole.
Did I skip a line? No, okay. ואין מתיכין לתוכן אבר. v'ein
matichin l'sochan avar. Also, you can't go ahead and use some lead,
you know, like you got these soldering irons and they would have
some lead. So you
can't, you know, use, melt it to get the vessel itself fixed,
you know, just use the material of the vessel itself and you
can't go ahead—this is why, of course, people died in the ancient
world because of all the lead poisoning—you can't go ahead and use
lead also as a way of filling it. Okay,
נפגמו, nifgemu, similarly if they got like a chip, okay, even not
a hole, אין מתקנין אותן, ein metaknin osan, you don't go ahead
and you fix them. Meaning as soon as something's got a problem,
you throw it out. You don't do any patching up. Okay, and
we'll see because of the whole idea that the בית המקדש is
supposed to, you know, represent this place of wealth and whatever, you
don't have stuff with patchwork on it, you know, you only use
nice new vessels.
Okay, סכין שנפגם אין משחיזין את פגימתו, Sakin shenifgam ein mashchizin es
pgimasov, and a knife got a nick, you don't go ahead and
you don't sharpen it. Now, רש״י Rashi actually is a little bothered
here. What, really? Something gets a little nick, you can't sharpen it
to remove the nick? So רש״י Rashi basically says that this thing
of not fixing the nicks is basically in a way that it'll
be obvious that something has been fixed. Okay, if you're basically just
a normal type of a sharpening and it's not obvious that you
fixed a problem, it's not like, 'Oh yeah, I see where you
got that chip and where you fixed it.' instead. No, it's like
it looks totally new, then that would not be an issue. Now,
נשמטה אין מחזירין
אותה. Nishmetah ein machzirin otah. Now this is also surprising. If the
blade of the knife fell off the handle, don't put it back
in the handle. Like, really? Like, you know, even if it's completely
a fix like it used to be? So presumably again not, like
we all know we've had things like, you know, once it slips
out, you put it back, but then it's never the way it
used to be and it's always slipping out again or it's always
a little loose, right? So if you could ממש mamash restore it,
presumably to its original state and it's not visible in any way,
then probably it's okay, although even there, you know, but the simple
sense of this is not that way. The simple sense of this
is don't do any repairs. You know, as soon as something is
a- like, you know, there's people like this. They're so wealthy, right,
that as soon as something is- like, I've worn it three times,
it's got a little thing, I'm not even going to bother throwing-
sending it to the cleaners. I don't care if it's going to
come back perfect. Like, it's no longer pristine. I'm throwing it out.
Okay.
One imagines you could at least, like, you know, reuse the material,
smelt it and refashion it from the beginning, but you're not going
to repair it. Okay.
אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, Abba Shaul said, סכין מטרפת הייתה
במקדש, Sakin metarefet haytah b'Mikdash, there used to be a knife in
the מקדש that was so, like,
delicate or sensitive that when you would שחט shacht an animal's neck,
it would cause a nick as it was שחטינג shachting the knife
itself, the blade itself would get nicked, and then it would cause
the animal to be a טרפה. treifah. ונמנו עליה כהנים וגנזוה, V'nimnu
aleha Kohanim u'genazuha, and they took a vote and they decided, oh,
we better get rid of this knife. No kidding, if it's causing
every animal to be a טרפה, treifah, not kidding, you gotta get
rid of it. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. בגדי כהונה אין עושים
מעשה מחט. Bigdei kehuna ein osim ma'aseh machat. In a similar way,
you don't go ahead and use and make the clothes through sewing.
Like, you know, you don't take different materials and you cut material
and you sew it together. It's all going to be weaved out
of one cloth, the entire garment. Okay. You know, this was- this
is like a real skill, right? You make the whole thing, like
the arms and whatever, everything is one- one unified, you know, one
sort of, you know, full piece that was weaved
together. I was just thinking about that. Like the מנורה, Menorah, it's
all one piece. אלא מעשה אורג, Ela ma'aseh oreg, it's all one
weaved
garment. שנאמר מעשה אורג. Shene'emar ma'aseh oreg. נתגאלו, Nitga'alu, if it became
somehow disgusting, it got some, you know, something,
you know, dirt, not just dirt, but whatever, what we'll see in
a minute, but something that makes it yucky. Okay, on it. That's
a technical term. אין מכבסין, Ein mechabsin, you don't laundry it. So
if the clothes get- gets- you know, this is what I was
talking about before. Once it gets disgusting, you don't even bother cleaning
it, you just- do a new one. לא בנתר ולא באהל, Lo
b'neter v'lo b'ohel, not using these various lyes or various types of
cleansers. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא במים מכבסין? Ha b'mayim
mechabsin? Does that mean that you can clean it with water? Why?
If you clean it with water by itself, it says don't use
the dyes? So what? It's okay to clean it with water? But
it won't even get as clean with just water. אמר אביי הכי
קאמר, Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar, הוגו, Hugu, אם במים מכבסין אותם בנתר
ואהל. im b'mayim mechabsin otam b'neter v'ohel. If it got to a
point that- that it is, you know, something that got dirty but
it could be cleaned with water, you know, a tiny little thing,
you put a little water, you could clean. Okay. If they got
disgusting, רש"י says the word הוגו hugu is from the word גועל,
gi'ul, okay, in a way that it doesn't really require vigorous cleansing,
just a little water could get it out. Okay. If it's that
type of a thing, not a serious stain, then you're allowed to
use cleansers to get it out and you could reuse it. Then
it's not like it really got a bad stain on it. Okay.
הוגו לנתר ואהל, Hugu l'neter v'ohel, but if it got disgusting that-
if it got some stain on it that's so whatever, problematic, that
it won't come out unless you use real serious cleansers, אף במים
אין מכבסין, Af b'mayim ein mechabsin, then you can't clean it in
any way. Okay. So it's a question of how disgusting is it.
What does it mean that, you know, once there's a little dirt
on your garment, you have to throw it out? I mean, that
would be a tremendous amount of waste. But what it means though
is that if it got stuff on it that is so dirty
that it can't be cleaned without serious cleansers, then you gotta sort
of get rid of it and get a new one. Did they
get blood on it all the time?
Yeah,
and that's a really good question. That's a really good question, you're
right.
I'm guessing they are, right?
They're getting blood on it. Yeah, I mean, you're right. I mean,
it went all the way right down to the bottom. Blood would
be splattering. I mean, does blood come out- blood actually is not
so hard to come out, but it doesn't just come out with
water. You do need- I mean, like sometimes if I get a
little- got a little bit, a little water and soap and you
scrape it out, it's not so hard to come out with blood,
but it's also not just water. Yeah, I don't know. That's an
excellent point. ויש אומרים אין מכבסין אותן כל עיקר, V'yesh omrim ein
mechabsin otam kol ikar, and some say, you know what? Even if
it is stuff that's easy to get out, you don't ever use-
laundry the clothes, שאין עניות במקום עשירות, She'ein aniyut b'makom ashirut, and
the general rule about all of this is that you do not-
you don't act like a poor person in a place of wealth.
You know, there's no poverty in a place of wealth, so if
the clothes get dirty, throw them out and do them all again.
But yeah, your question about the blood is an excellent one. Like,
you know, literally, what do you do? You make new garments, I
mean, every single day? Like, it's insane, right? And it's clean. It's
clear from other evidence that they had places where they kept their
garments and whatever and that they, I mean it's right, it speaks
about like if they get so worn out, you know, that then
they would use them for like, you know, the wicks for the,
you know, for
like the שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva or whatever. Yeah, it's
strange to imagine that they didn't laundry them at all. I don't
know if your notes say anything, but it's an excellent question. Okay,
now that we're talking about the garments, we're going to end with
a little אגדתא, agadata, okay? תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Or well first
we'll discuss how the מעיל me'il was made that כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol wore and then we'll end with some אגדתא. agadata. מעיל כולו
של תכלת היה. Me'il kulo shel techeiles haya. The מעיל me'il was
all of sky blue, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, ויעש את מעיל האפוד כליל תכלת.
vaya'as es me'il ha'ephod kelil techeiles. שוליו כיצד? shulav keitzad? How would
you make the hem, which would be an alternation, an alternating of
pomegranates and bells? Right? That's the way the תורה Torah describes it.
So how would you do it? מביא תכלת וארגמן ותולעת שני. mevi
techeiles ve'argaman ve'tola'as shani. You'd bring these three things, right? The sky
blue, and the ארגמן argaman is like the purple, and the תולעת
שני tola'as shani is the red, שזורין, shezurin, and you'd have them
all like spun together. And this would be the stuff, you know,
that you would make, the thing itself would be all of sky
blue, but the pomegranates would be these three threads spun together, three
colors. ועושה אותן כמין רימונים שלא פתחו פיהן, ve'oseh osan kemin rimonim
she'lo pitchu pihen, and you make them like pomegranates that the mouth,
like the top, hasn't yet begun to like open up a little
bit. Totally, you know, so pretty much like complete balls I guess
without even the opening of the top that happens by a pomegranate.
וכמין קובעות של קסדות, ve'chemin kova'os shel kasdos, and like it
says the type of a like of a cone, קובעות, kova'os, cones
that were on helmets, okay? Steinsaltz has a pretty picture, I looked
it up. Anyways, I don't exactly get what that's supposed... שבראשי תינוקות,
she'berashei tinokos, like the helmets that little kids would wear, the cones
on top of them. I'm not exactly sure how that is, what
that's clarifying. I mean they're supposed to look like pomegranates, so I'm
not exactly sure what point that's making specifically about looking like cones.
Anyway, ומביא שבעים ושנים זוגין, u'mevi shivim u'shnayim zugim, and you bring
72 bells, שבהן שבעים ושנים ענבלין, she'bahen shivim u'shnayim inbalin, that have
in them 72 clappers. I mean tiny little bells, you know. ותולה
בהן שלשים וששה מצד זה ושלשים וששה מצד זה. ve'toleh bahen shloshim
ve'shishah mitzad zeh ve'shloshim ve'shishah mitzad zeh. And you have 36 bells
on one side and 36 on the other. Like you know, it
would be like it would have two sides, the tunic, okay? And
all, you would alternate bells and pomegranates, okay? So you'd have 72
on each on each side. 36 pomegranates and 36 bells on each
side and alternating them. רבי דוסא אומר משום רבי יהודה שלשים וששה
היו. Rabbi Dosa omer mishum Rabbi Yehudah shloshim ve'shishah hayu. No no
no, the total was 36 bells and 36 pomegranates. שמונה עשרה מצד
זה ושמונה עשרה מצד זה. shmoneh esreih mitzad zeh u'shmoneh esreih mitzad
zeh. Okay, fine. 18 on a side.
אמר רב עיניני בר ששון, Amar Rav Inini bar Sasson, כמחלוקת כאן
כך מחלוקת בצרעת. kemachlokes kan kach machlokes be'tzara'as. The same way there's
a question of 72 or
36 or whatever, there's a question by the different types
of ways of the appearances of the
נגעים. nega'im. דתנן מראות נגעים רבי דוסא בן הרכינס אומר ל"ו, detnan
mar'os nega'im Rabbi Dosa ben Horkinas omer lamed vav, 36. עקביא
בן מהללאל אומר שבעים ושנים, Akavya ben Mahalalel omer shivim u'shnayim, 72.
Okay, we're going to see in a minute why we might be
drawing a comparison to נגעים. nega'im. ואמר רבי עיניני בר ששון, ve'amar
Rabbi Inini bar Sasson, למה נסמכה? lama nismacha? So since we quoted
עיניני בר ששון, Inini bar Sasson, until now we were sort of
just dealing with you know, the vessel and how did you clean
it or how did you make it. But now it's the same
אמורא Amora and it's going to allow us to end with a
little piece of אגדתא agadata and talking about something about the power
of the garments of the כהנים, kohanim, which is funny because a
minute ago we were talking about the actual vessels that we used
you know, with the blood and the flour and the this and
the that. And now we're talking with a very different type of
vessel as it were, the clothes of the כהנים. kohanim. And we're
very much shifting our focus. So let's take a look.
למה נסמכה פרשת קרבנות לפרשת בגדי כהונה? lama nismacha parashas korbanos le'parashas
bigdei kehunah? Why was when it speaks about the sacrifices in צו
Tzav and immediately at the end of צו Tzav it speaks about
the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah and the בגדים begadim that you make
and you know whatever. It's one thing in שמות Shemos where it
talks about making the vessels of the בית המקדש and making the
בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. It's all the various things that had to
be fashioned for the בית המקדש. But in צו, Tzav, it speaks
about the bringing of the קרבנות korbanos and then the second half
of צו Tzav is all about the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah and
dressing אהרן Aharon and you know whatever and clothing them with their
בגדים begadim and so on. So why were those juxtaposed? לומר לך
מה קרבנות מכפרים אף בגדי כהונה מכפרים. lomar lacha mah korbanos mechaperim
af bigdei kehunah mechaperim. To tell you: the same way קרבנות korbanos
atone, the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah atone. כתונת מכפרת על שפיכות דמים.
kesones mechaperes al shefichus damim. The כתונת, kesones, which is the basic
tunic that every כהן kohen would wear, that was for the spilling
of blood. שנאמר וישחטו שעיר עזים ויטבלו את הכתונת בדם. she'ne'emar vayishchatu
se'ir izim vayitbelu es hakesones badam. Right? This is by you know,
by יוסף. Yosef. They slaughtered it and they dipped the כתונת kesones
in blood. So somehow because it was used to cover up somehow
for you know, murder or like pseudo-murder, I mean certainly the spilling
of blood or the almost spilling of blood of יוסף Yosef himself
and the spilling of blood of you know, of the animal that
they slaughtered, this also brings about atonement for the spilling of blood.
The מהרש"א Maharsha says you know, it's because the כתונת. kesones. Which
is like a tunic is the thing closest to the body. So
if you were to actually murder somebody, you know, God forbid, right,
the כתונת Kotonet would be the thing that would get all blood.
And if you want to sort of think about it, it like
it most represents a person's body because it is the thing that
goes right up against the person's body. Okay, so therefore this is
like represents the body of a person and therefore that atones for
murder.
We'll see in a minute what it means to atone for murder.
It doesn't mean a person commits murder and they're forgiven because the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because the כהן Kohen is wearing a כתונת.
Kotonet. Basically, just to jump a little ahead, what it means is
that it atones for the communal responsibility for murder. Somebody commits murder,
it's the community's own responsibility that they let that happen, that they
didn't prosecute somebody, they didn't instill enough law and order and so
on. So for this sense of communal, shared communal responsibility, the כתונת
Kotonet atones. Okay.
מכנסיים, Michnasayim,
the, the like, you know, the breeches as they say, מכפר על
גילוי עריות, Mechaper al gilluy arayot, that is for sins of the,
you know, sexual sins, because that's where it is. It covers up
the sexual organs. שנאמר ועשה להם
מכנסי בד לכסות בשר ערווה, Shene'emar: Ve'asei lahem michnesei vad lechasot besar
ervah, to cover up the flesh of nakedness. Okay. So again, presumably
this does not mean the, you know, individual sins, this means the
sort of communal responsibility around this issue. Okay.
That's basically the point that תוספות makes that these are all referring
to like communal responsibility.
מצנפת, Mitznefet, the miter, you know, the hat, the like the hat,
מכפר על גסי הרוח. Mechaper al gasei haruach. That's for arrogance. Okay,
which is clear, like it goes on the top of your head.
So מניין? Minayin? אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabi Chanina, יבוא דבר שבגובה
ויכפר על גובה, Yavo davar shebegovah veychaper al govah, something at a
height and atone on a person that is too arrogant, that makes
themselves too haughty. אבנט Avnet מכפר על הרהור הלב. Mechaper al hirhur
halev. The belt is on sort of, you know, evil intentions and
thoughts, which is funny that that needs atoning, right? I mean sometimes
we say an עולה Olah atones for a הרהור הלב. hirhur halev.
On the other hand we sometimes say that God doesn't treat evil
thoughts as if you did it. Maybe the point is He doesn't
treat it as if you did it, but it doesn't mean that
it's nothing. You know, also one wonders if the question is specifically
about like illicit sexual thoughts or does it just like mean, you
know, any types of thoughts of sin or whatever.
Anyway, where do you get that from?
היכא דאיתיה, Heicha de'iteih, because that's where it's put. You put the
belt close to the heart. It's funny, a belt you'd think it's
down here, but actually the belt is closer to like around here
like where the elbows are, so it's close to the heart, so
it has to do with the thoughts of the heart. Okay. So
those are what is what's worn by normal כהנים, Kohanim, okay? The,
the basic tunic, the miter, the belt, and the, and the breeches.
Now by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. חושן, Choshen, the חושן, Choshen,
right? מכפר על הדינים, Mechaper al hadinim, which is, you know, which
you got all of the jewels or whatever, מכפר על הדינים, Mechaper
al hadinim, on a perversion of justice. שנאמר ועשית
חושן משפט, Shene'emar: Ve'asita choshen mishpat, the חושן Choshen of justice. Okay,
so it's about perversion of justice. אפוד, Efod, which is the, also
which is like the apron worn by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
מכפר על עבודת כוכבים, Mechaper al avodat kochavim, on idolatry. שנאמר אין
אפוד ותרפים, Shene'emar: Ein efod utrafim, there is no אפוד Efod and
תרפים Trafim and like, and, and idols. So because as I think
the מהרש"א Maharsha points out or whatever, you know, it's clear from
other verses that this would be a standard garment worn also by
idolatrous priests, the אפוד. Efod. So on the one hand it's just
associated with idols, on the other hand the way it's being read
in this verse, because there is no אפוד, Efod, you are going
to be punished for your
idolatry. מעיל, Me'il,
you know the מעיל, Me'il, which is what we were talking about
before, right? The blue tunic,
מכפר על לשון הרע, Mechaper al lashon hara, for evil speech. מניין?
Minayin? אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabi Chanina, יבוא דבר שבקול, Yavo davar
shebekol, it makes sound, right? It even says ונשמע קולו בבואו אל
הקודש, Venishma kolo bevo'o el hakodesh, you know, when he's walking, it
makes, the bells make sound,
ויכפר על קול הרע, Veychaper al kol hara, and it will atone
for the evil sound, the evil voice, evil speech. This by the
way, I think the מהרש"א Maharsha points out, is why the גמרא
Gemara made a comparison before to the צרעת, Tzara'at, right? The 36
or the 72 different types of צרעת Tzara'at because צרעת Tzara'at is
also for לשון הרע. Lashon hara.
וציץ, Vetzitz, and the, the ציץ, Tzitz, right, the gold thing on
the forehead, מכפר על עזות פנים, Mechaper al azut panim, on brazenness,
which is interesting. Brazenness is different than haughtiness, right? You could be
haughty but not act in a brazen חוצפה Chutzpah type of a
way. בציץ
כתיב והיה על מצח אהרן, Betzitz ketiv: Vehayah al metzach Aharon, on
the forehead. ובעזות פנים כתיב ומצח אשה זונה היה לך, Uve'azut panim
ketiv: Umetzach ishah zonah hayah lach, and the forehead of a woman
prostitute you had. So the forehead is symbolic of the sense of
being brazen. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says, ואיני, Ve'eini, is
this really true that these things atone for שפיכות דמים Shefichut damim
and whatever? ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ve'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi,
שני דברים לא מצינו להם כפרה בקרבנות Shenei devarim lo matzinu lahem
kaparah bekorbanot and the forehead of a woman prostitute you had to
use so the forehead is symbolic of the sense of being brazen.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says ואיני ve'eini is this really
true that these things atone for שפיכות דמים shifichus damim and whatever
ואמר רבי יהושע בן לוי ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi שני דברים
לא מצינו להם כפרה בקרבנות shenei devarim lo matzinu lahem kappara bekorbanot
for two things we did not find atonement for in the sacrifices
ומצינו לו כפרה ממקום אחר umatzinu lo kappara mimakom acher and we
found it elsewhere ואלו הן שפיכות דמים ולשון הרע ve'eilu hen shifichus
damim velashon hara שפיכות דמים shifichus damim and evil speech. Again, the
interesting comparison of שפיכות דמים shifichus damim and לשון הרע lashon hara
because you know לשון הרע lashon hara obviously could destroy a person's
reputation and so on. שפיכות דמים מעגלה ערופה ולשון הרע מקטורת shifichus
damim me'egla arufa velashon hara miketoret and לשון הרע lashon hara from
קטורת. ketoret. דתני רבי חנינא מניין לקטורת שמכפרת detani Rabbi Chanina minayin
laketoret shemechaperet so עגלה ערופה egla arufa שפיכות דמים shifichus damim is
obvious. But
by the way, again as תוספות points out, that doesn't atone for
the actual murderer. That atones for communal responsibility, which is why תוספות
says that a lot of what we're talking about here also is
not that it atones for the sinner, it atones for the communal
responsibility associated with these sins. Okay, and where do you get לשון
הרע lashon hara the קטורת? ketoret? ולשון הרע מקטורת דתני רבי חנינא
מניין לקטורת שמכפרת הוי אומר קטורת מכפרת שנאמר
velashon hara miketoret detani
Rabbi Chanina minayin laketoret shemechaperet hevei omer ketoret mechaperet shene'emar by אהרן
Aharon we read this recently ויתן את הקטורת ויכפר על העם. vayiten
et haketoret vayichaper al ha'am. ותני דבי רבי ישמעאל על מה קטורת
מכפרת vetani devei Rabbi Yishmael al ma ketoret mechaperet what did it
atone for? על לשון הרע al lashon hara evil speech. Now normally
לשון הרע lashon hara we translate to mean the gossip. But actually
that's the influence also of the חפץ חיים Chofetz Chaim that he
very much made this whole thing לשון הרע lashon hara is gossip,
מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra slander, but לשון הרע lashon hara
in the גמרא Gemara also just means all forms of evil speech.
Okay, so for example the לשון הרע lashon hara here by the
קטורת ketoret was when they used their words to actually attack משה
Moshe and אהרן Aharon and they said אתם המיתם את עם ה',
atem hamitem et am Hashem, you've killed God's people and that led
this whole plague to come out. So it's not only limited to
slander. Anyway you see that the קטורת ketoret atones, so the question
is: so what is it? Here we're saying עגלה ערופה egla arufa
and קטורת ketoret and you said it was the מעיל me'il and
the and the what do you call it and the כתונת. ketonet.
So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא לשון הרע לשון הרע קשיא שפיכות
דמים שפיכות דמים. kashia lashon hara lashon hara kashia shifichus damim shifichus
damim. So
which one is it? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo
kashia, it's not difficult. הא דידיע מאן קטליה הא דלא ידיע מאן
קטליה. ha deyedia man katlei ha delo yedia man katlei. The עגלה
ערופה egla arufa is you don't know who murdered him, but that's
the עגלה ערופה egla arufa atones. When you know who the murderer
is, then the מעיל me'il atones. So the גמרא Gemara says: wait
a minute, if you know why the murderer is, why is anything
atoning? It's your responsibility to take care of it, okay? אי דידיע
מאן קטליה בר קטלא הוא. ei deyedia man katlei bar katala hu.
You should go ahead and be and again the way תוספות is
reading it, it's not atoning for the person, it's atoning for the
ציבור. tzibur. But why does the רש"י says the same thing. Why
does the ציבור tzibur get off the hook and why do they
get atonement if you know who killed the guy? So go ahead
and prosecute him if you know who the murderer is. So the
גמרא Gemara says במזיד ולא אזהרו ביה. bemezid velo azhero bei. No,
no, no, he did it but we can't prosecute him, okay? If
it was a שוגג shogeg we could send him to an עיר
מקלט. ir miklat. If it was a מזיד mezid and he was
warned we could execute him. But he was מזיד mezid and he
wasn't warned so we can't we can't prosecute him but we bear
as a community responsibility. But you can't say: so on the one
hand you don't get off the hook as a community if there's
something you could still be doing. But at this stage there's nothing
we could be doing but we still own responsibility for having allowed
it to occur. And therefore for that the כתונת ketonet atones. Okay,
לשון הרע לשון הרע. lashon hara lashon hara. Now לשון
הרע lashon hara what is it? Is it the קטורת ketoret or
is it the מעיל? me'il? So the גמרא Gemara says נמי לא
קשיא הא בצינא הא בפרהסיא. nami lo kashia ha betzina ha befarhesia.
If it's a private לשון הרע lashon hara so then there is
okay so then it's the קטורת ketoret which is the phrase before
is did I skip a line by the קטורת? ketoret?
No, I don't think so. It says יבוא דבר שבחשאי ויכפר על
מעשה חשאי. yavo davar shebachashai veyekhaber al maaseh chashai.
I might have not read that line before. The reason the קטורת
ketoret atones for
לשון הרע lashon hara is the same with לשון הרע lashon hara
is often told in private, right? People aren't publicly sort of spreading
their לשון הרע. lashon hara. So the קטורת ketoret also is brought
in private because normally the קטורת ketoret is brought into the היכל
heichal and it says no כהנים kohanim are allowed to be there,
not just on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, in general when the קטורת
ketoret is brought people are not allowed to be there when the
קטורת ketoret is being brought. So that's the קטורת ketoret atones for
that is brought in private atones for לשון הרע lashon hara that
is spread in private. So the גמרא says fine, that's לשון הרע
lashon hara spread in private that the קטורת ketoret atones for. But
לשון הרע lashon hara that is spread publicly, that you need the
מעיל me'il to atone for. Okay and therefore each one of them
does a certain degree of atonement. And again the way that תוספות
explains it is we're not talking about a forgiving for the actual
perpetrator, we're talking about the communal responsibility. The last thing I'll say
הדרן לך מזבח מקדש. hadran lach mizbeiach mekadesh. The last thing I'll
say here is I find it fascinating, you know, that
the entire מסכת masechet as we've been dealing with has been very
technical, you know, it's like okay does this work does this not
work what makes this פסול what makes this not פסול? I mean
that's what הלכה is. But it never actually, you know, really had
a discussion about what I mean what is it atoning for, what
types of sins. I mean to the degree it is you know
a חטאת chatas comes for something that you're חייב כרת chayav kares
or whatever. But you know the high focus is on the technical
aspects and not on the question of like is this cleansing me
of various types of things. And here at the end we talk
about when we're talking about sins that first of all we can
relate to you know I mean hopefully not too related too much
to. murder, but things, you know, but I mean things like לשון
הרע, Lashon Hara, הרהור הלב, Hirhur Halev, גילוי עריות, Giluy Arayot, those
aren't the technical questions of are you חייב כרת chayav kares or
not to get a חטאת, Chatas, right? These are the types of
sins that as normal people we sort of struggle with or challenge
with or whatever, and it also translates it in terms of the
way these atonements are achieved, not by something sort of obscure like
קרבנות, Korbanot, or something out of our normal realm of experience, but
about certain types of clothing, you know? Now, of course you could
say you don't have בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehuna either nowadays, but I
think actually, I mean my personal sense is that the גמרא sometimes
makes these implicit or explicit comparisons between let's say the ציצית Tzitzit
and the בגדים Bigadim of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and also
the תפילין, Tefillin, like the תפילין Tefillin like the מצנפת Mitznefet and
so on, and in general thinking about the question about like how
we dress and how we comport ourselves, and how we demonstrate, you
know, dressing is also like how you represent yourself to the community,
right? And if you're thinking about this as a sense of communal
responsibility. Anyway, I think the point of saying all of these things
is to actually say like, all of this is important in terms
of the technical halachic of קרבנות. Korbanot. How do we actually think
about sin nowadays and our sense of like where does atonement come
from? And it's actually interesting in dealing with this collection of these
sins that are more like real and relevant, right? And it translates
it into questions about clothing, you know, which is also something more
accessible and real and relevant and about behavior and about comporting oneself
and so on. So anyway, it doesn't exactly connect all the dots,
I'm not exactly connecting all the dots, but I think it's suggestive,
this type of explicit discussion around real issues of sin and real
types of sins that we're thinking about and not technical כרת, kares,
not כרת kares categories etcetera, and dealing with it in something that's
more accessible than just the discussion like of קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay, so
we will end with this and continue with